I want to take you all on a journey to the place I was raised, northwest Pakistan, called Dir. Dir was founded in the 17th century. It was a princely state until its merger with Pakistan in 1969. Our prince, Nawab Shah Jahan, reserved the right to wear white, the color of honor, but only for himself. He didn't believe in educating his people. And at the time of my birth in 1979, only five percent of boys and one percent of girls received any schooling at all. I was one among that one percent. Growing up, I was very close to my father. He is a pharmacy doctor, and he sent me to school. Every day, I would go to his clinic when my lessons finished. He's a wonderful man and a well-respected community leader. He was leading a welfare organization, and I would go with him to the social and political gatherings to listen and talk to the local men about our social and economic problems. However, when I was 16, my father asked me to stop coming with him to the public gatherings. Now, I was a young woman, and my place was in the home. I was very upset. But most of my family members, they were happy with this decision. It was very difficult for me to sit back in the home and not be involved. It took two years that finally my family agreed that my father could reconnect me with women and girls, so they could share their problems and together we could resolve them. So, with his blessings, I started to reconnect with women and girls so we could resolve their problems together. When women show up, they bring their realities and views with them. And yet, I have found all too often, women underestimate their own strength, their potential and their self-respect. However, while connecting with these women and girls, it became very clear to me that if there was to be any hope to create a better life for these women and girls and their families, we must stand up for our own rights -- and not wait for someone else to come and help us. So I took a huge leap of faith and founded my own organization in '94 to create our very own platform for women empowerment. I engaged many women and girls to work with me. It was hard. Many of the women working with me had to leave once they got married, because their husbands wouldn't let them work. One colleague of mine was given away by her family to make amends for a crime her brother had committed. I couldn't help her. And I felt so helpless at that time. But it made me more determined to continue my struggle. I saw many practices like these, where these women suffered silently, bearing this brutality. But when I see a woman struggling to change her situation instead of giving up, it motivates me. So I ran for a public office as an independent candidate in Lower Dir in the local elections in 2001. Despite all the challenges and hurdles I faced throughout this process, I won. (Applause) And I served in the public office for six years. But unfortunately, we women, elected women, we were not allowed to sit in the council together with all the members and to take part in the proceedings. We had to sit in a separate, ladies-only room, not even aware what was happening in the council. Men told me that, "You women, elected women members, should buy sewing machines for women." When I knew what they needed the most was access to clean drinking water. So I did everything I could do to prioritize the real challenges these women faced. I set up five hand pumps in the two dried up wells in my locality. Well, we got them working again.
Quiero llevarlos a un viaje al lugar donde me crie, llamado Dir, en el noroeste de Pakistán. Dir fue fundado en el siglo XVII. Fue un estado principesco hasta su unificación con Pakistán en 1969. Nuestro príncipe, Nawab Shah Jahan, había reservado el derecho de vestir de blanco, el color del honor, pero solo para sí mismo. No creía en educar a su gente. Y en el momento de mi nacimiento, en 1979, solo un 5 % de los niños y un 1 % de las niñas recibían enseñanza escolar. Yo estuve entre ese 1 %. Al crecer, era muy apegada a mi padre. Es un médico de farmacia y me envió al colegio. Cada día, al terminar mis lecciones, iba a su consultorio. Es un hombre maravilloso, y un líder de la comunidad muy respetado. Lideraba una organización para la asistencia social, y yo iba con él a las reuniones políticas y sociales para escuchar y hablar con los hombres locales sobre nuestros problemas sociales y económicos. Sin embargo, cuando cumplí los 16 años, mi padre me pidió que dejara de ir con él a las reuniones públicas. Ahora era una mujer joven, y mi lugar estaba en el hogar. Me sentí muy molesta. Pero la mayoría de los miembros de mi familia apoyaban esta decisión. Fue muy difícil para mí, sentarme en casa y no estar involucrada. Pasaron dos años hasta que finalmente mi familia accedió a que mi padre me reconectara con otras mujeres y chicas, para que pudieran compartir sus problemas y poder resolverlos juntas. Así que, con su bendición, empecé a reconectarme con mujeres y chicas así podíamos resolver juntas sus problemas. Cuando las mujeres se presentan, traen sus realidades y puntos de vista. Y, sin embargo, encontré muy a menudo que las mujeres subestiman su propia fortaleza, su potencial y su autorrespeto. Sin embargo, al conectarme con estas mujeres y chicas me quedó muy claro que si había alguna esperanza de crear una vida mejor para estas mujeres y chicas, y para sus familias, debíamos defender nuestros derechos, y no esperar a que alguien viniera a ayudarnos. Así que decidí arriesgarme y fundé mi propia organización en 1994, para crear nuestra propia plataforma para potenciar a las mujeres. Llamé a muchas mujeres y chicas para que trabajaran conmigo. Fue duro. Muchas de las mujeres que trabajaban conmigo debían dejarlo cuando se casaban, porque sus esposos no las dejaban trabajar. Una de mis colegas había sido entregada por su familia como compensación por un crimen que había cometido su hermano. No la pude ayudar. Y en ese momento me sentí muy impotente. Pero eso me convenció aún más para continuar con mi lucha. Vi muchas prácticas como esta, donde estas mujeres sufrían en silencio, soportando esta brutalidad. Pero cuando veo una mujer luchando por cambiar su situación en lugar de rendirse, eso me motiva. Así que me postulé para un cargo público como candidata independiente en el distrito del Bajo Dir en las elecciones locales de 2001. A pesar de los desafíos y obstáculos que enfrenté durante este proceso, gané. (Aplausos) Y estuve en ese cargo público durante seis años. Pero, desafortunadamente, a nosotras, las mujeres electas, no se nos permitía sentarnos en el concejo con todos los miembros y participar en los debates. Debíamos sentarnos en una sala aparte, solo para damas, sin saber lo que pasaba en el concejo. Los hombres me dijeron: "Uds., las mujeres electas, deberían comprar máquinas de coser para mujeres". Y yo sabía que lo que más necesitaban era el acceso al agua potable. Así que hice todo lo que pude para dar prioridad a los desafíos reales que enfrentaban estas mujeres. Instalé cinco bombas manuales en los dos pozos secos de mi localidad. Bien, conseguimos que funcionaran otra vez.
Before long, we made water accessible for over 5,000 families. We proved that anything the men could do, so could we women. I built alliances with other elected women members, and last year, we women were allowed to sit together with all the members in the council. (Applause) And to take part in the legislation and planning and budgeting, in all the decisions. I saw there is strength in numbers. You know yourselves. Lack of representation means no one is fighting for you. Pakistan is -- We're 8,000 miles away from where I'm here with you today. But I hope what I'm about to tell you will resonate with you, though we have this big distance in miles and in our cultures. When women show up, they bring the realities and hopes of half a population with them. In 2007, we saw the rise of the Taliban in Swat, Dir and nearby districts. It was horrifying. The Taliban killed innocent people. Almost every day, people collected the dead bodies of their loved ones from the streets. Most of the social and political leaders struggling and working for the betterment of their communities were threatened and targeted. Even I had to leave, leaving my children behind with my in-laws. I closed my office in Dir and relocated to Peshawar, the capital of my province. I was in trauma, kept thinking what to do next. And most of the family members and friends were suggesting, "Shad, stop working. The threat is very serious." But I persisted. In 2009, we experienced a historic influx of internally displaced persons, from Swat, Dir and other nearby districts. I started visiting the camps almost every day, until the internally displaced persons started to go back to their place of origin. I established four mother-child health care units, especially to take care of over 10,000 women and children nearby the camps. But you know, during all these visits, I observed that there was very little attention towards women's needs. And I was looking for what is the reason behind it. And I found it was because of the underrepresentation of women in both social and political platforms, in our society as a whole. And that was the time when I realized that I need to narrow down my focus on building and strengthening women's political leadership to increase their political representation, so they would have their own voice in their future. So we started training around 300 potential women and youth for the upcoming local elections in 2015. And you know what? Fifty percent of them won. (Applause) And they are now sitting in the councils, taking part actively in the legislation, planning and budgeting. Most of them are now investing their funds on women's health, education, skill development and safe drinking water. All these elected women now share, discuss and resolve their problems together. Let me tell you about two of the women I have been working with: Saira Shams. You can see, this young lady, age 26, she ran for a public office in 2015 in Lower Dir, and she won. She completed two of the community infrastructure schemes. You know, women, community infrastructure schemes ... Some people think this is men's job. But no, this is women's job, too, we can do it. And she also fixed two of the roads leading towards girls schools, knowing that without access to these schools, they are useless to the girls of Dir. And another young woman is Asma Gul. She is a very active member of the young leaders forum we established. She was unable to run for the public office, so she has become the first female journalist of our region. She speaks and writes for women's and girls' issues and their rights. Saira and Asma, they are the living examples of the importance of inclusion and representation. Let me tell you this, too. In the 2013 general elections in Pakistan and the local elections in 2015, there were less than 100 women voters in Dir. But you know what? I'm proud to tell you that this year, during the general elections, there were 93,000 women voters in Dir. (Applause) So our struggle is far from over. But this shift is historic. And a sign that women are standing up, showing up and making it absolutely clear that we all must invest in building women's leadership. In Pakistan and here in the United States, and everywhere in the world, this means women in politics, women in business and women in positions of power making important decisions. It took me 23 years to get here. But I don't want any girl or any woman to take 23 years of her life to make herself heard. I have had some dark days. But I have spent every waking moment of my life
En poco tiempo hicimos que 5000 familias tuvieran acceso al agua. Probamos que cualquier cosa que pudieran hacer los hombres nosotras también podíamos hacerlas. Hice alianzas con otras mujeres electas, y el año pasado nos permitieron sentarnos con todos los miembros del concejo. (Aplausos) Y participar en la legislación, en el planeamiento y en el presupuesto, en todas las decisiones. Vi que ser numeroso fortalece. Ya lo saben. La ausencia de representación significa que nadie lucha por Uds. Pakistán es... está a casi 13 000 km de donde estoy hoy aquí, con Uds., pero espero que lo que les contaré resonará en Uds., aunque tengamos esta gran distancia en kilómetros y en nuestras culturas. Cuando las mujeres se presentan traen con ellas la realidad y las esperanzas de media población. En 2007 vimos el ascenso de los talibanes en Swat, en Dir y en los distritos cercanos. Fue horrible. Los talibanes mataron a gente inocente. Casi todos los días la gente recogía en las calles los cadáveres de sus seres queridos. La mayoría de los líderes políticos y sociales que luchaban y trabajaban para mejorar sus comunidades fueron amenazados y atacados. Incluso yo tuve que irme, y dejar a mis hijos con mis suegros. Cerré mi oficina en Dir y me trasladé a Peshawar, la capital de mi provincia. Estaba traumatizada, pensando en qué era lo siguiente que debía hacer. Y la mayoría de los miembros de mi familia y mis amigos sugerían: "Shad, deja de trabajar. La amenaza es muy seria". Pero persistí. En 2009, tuvimos una afluencia histórica de personas desplazadas internamente, desde Swat, Dir y otros distritos cercanos. Empecé a visitar los campamentos casi todos los días, hasta que las personas desplazadas internamente comenzaron a regresar a su lugar de origen. Establecí cuatro unidades de salud para madres e hijos, especialmente para cuidar de las más de 10 000 mujeres y niños de los alrededores de los campamentos. Pero durante todas estas visitas observé que las necesidades de las mujeres recibían muy poca atención. Y busqué la razón detrás de eso. Y encontré que se debía a que las mujeres estaban poco representadas en las plataformas sociales y políticas, y en nuestra sociedad en su conjunto. Y en ese momento me di cuenta de que debía centrarme exclusivamente en construir y reforzar el liderazgo político de las mujeres para aumentar su representación política, de manera que en el futuro pudieran tener su propia voz. Así que empezamos a entrenar a unas 300 mujeres y jóvenes para las elecciones inminentes de 2015. ¿Y saben qué? El 50 % de ellas ganó. (Aplausos) Y ahora están sentadas en los concejos, tomando parte activa en la legislación, el planeamiento y el presupuesto. La mayoría de ellas invierten sus fondos en la salud de las mujeres, educación, capacitación y agua potable. Todas estas mujeres electas ahora comparten, discuten y resuelven juntas sus problemas. Les contaré sobre dos de las mujeres con las que he estado trabajando: Saira Shams. Esta mujer joven de 26 años se presentó como candidata en 2015 en el Bajo Dir, y ganó. Completó dos de los esquemas de infraestructura de la comunidad. Ya saben: mujeres... esquemas de infraestructura de la comunidad... Algunos piensan que este es un trabajo de hombres. Pero no, es también un trabajo de mujeres, también podemos hacerlo. Y también reparó dos de los caminos que conducen a las escuelas para niñas, porque sabía que, sin acceso a ellas, estas escuelas son inútiles para las niñas de Dir. Y otra de las jóvenes es Asma Gul. Ella es un miembro muy activo del fórum de líderes jóvenes que establecimos. No pudo postularse para un cargo público, así que se convirtió en la primera mujer periodista de nuestra región. Habla y escribe sobre los problemas de las mujeres y las chicas y sus derechos. Saira y Asma son ejemplos vivos de la importancia de la inclusión y la representación. También les diré esto: en la elección general de 2013 en Pakistán y en las elecciones locales de 2015 hubo menos de 100 votos femeninos en Dir. Pero ¿saben qué? Estoy orgullosa de decirles que este año, durante las elecciones locales, hubo 93 000 mujeres que votaron en Dir. (Aplausos) Así que nuestra lucha está lejos de haber terminado. Pero este cambio es histórico. Y es también una señal de que las mujeres están luchando, apareciendo y dejando en claro que todos debemos invertir en la creación de un liderazgo femenino. En Pakistán, y aquí, en los EE. UU., y en cualquier lugar del mundo, esto significa mujeres en política, mujeres en negocios y mujeres en posiciones de poder tomando decisiones importantes. Me tomó 23 años llegar aquí. Pero no quiero que a ninguna chica o mujer le lleve 23 años de su vida para hacerse oír. He tenido algunos días oscuros. Pero he pasado cada día de mi vida
working for the right of every woman to live her full potential. Imagine with me a world where thousands of us stand up and they support other young women together, creating opportunities and choices that benefit all. And that, my friends, can change the world.
trabajando por el derecho de cada mujer a vivir a su capacidad máxima. Imaginen junto conmigo un mundo donde miles de nosotras nos levantamos y apoyamos en conjunto a otras jóvenes, creando oportunidades y opciones que beneficien a todos. Y eso, mis amigos, puede cambiar el mundo.
Thank you. (Applause)
Gracias. (Aplausos)